A Guide to the Meridian Institute / Health and Rejuvenation Research Center Collection, 1989-2015
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
Meridian Institute / Health and Rejuvenation Research Center Collection, 1989-2015
The Edgar Cayce Foundation, Virginia Beach, Virginia
Coll. 27
5.2 Linear Feet 13 boxes.
Mein, Eric; Thompson, Deborah; Richards, Douglas;McMillin, David; Nelson, Carl; Eschelman, Marie
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by material type.
Biographical / Historical
The Meridian Institute operated as a Virginia Beach non-profit organization dedicated to researching holistic and integrative approaches to wellness and healing. With a focus on researching the body-mind-spirit connection, the institute researched various modalities and systems including the holistic philosophy of Edgar Cayce, traditional osteopathy, chiropractic, herbal medicine, mind-body healing, and spiritual transformation.
The institute was founded in 1994, operated for 10 years, and included Eric Mein, MD, Douglas Richards, PhD, Carl Nelson, DC, and David McMillin. Headed by Dr. Mein, a Virginia Beach physician, Mein had also served as scholar-in-residence at Atlantic University, and wrote Keys to Health: The Challenge and Promise of Holism, based on the Edgar Cayce medical readings. The Director of Research was Dr. Richards, who had been on the faculty of Atlantic University and had also served as the university's director of research. Dr. Nelson, a Virginia Beach chiropractor, served as the institute's clinical researcher, and McMillin served as independent researcher and Cayce scholar.
During its time in operation, the Meridian Institute undertook a number of leading-edge research projects that examined the body-mind-spirit connection, including the following:
• Radial Appliance Project • Psoriasis Project • Migraine Project • Epilepsy Project • Multiple Sclerosis Project • Parkinson's Disease Project • Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Project • Asthma Project • Arthritis Project • Hypertension Project • Irritable Bowel Syndrome Project • Manual Therapy Project
Related Materials
See Meridian Institute digital library hosted by the A.R.E. Library: https://www.meridianinstitute.com/
Scope and Contents
This collection includes research data, research participant files, reports, and office files generated by the Meridian Institute and the Health and Rejuvenation Research Center during operations between 1994 and 2004.
- general health inventories A-Z, 1999-2002; Includes individual patient files.
  - Box 1
  - Box 2
  - Box 3
  - Box 4
  - Box 5
  - Box 6
- office files, 1989-2015
  - Box 7
    - aphonia background questionnaire, 2004; Folder 7:1
    - approach to life inventory, undated; Folder 7:2
    - by-laws [American Holistic Nurses' Association], 1997; Folder 7:3
    - certificate [American Holistic Nurses' Association] Deborah Thompson, 1998; Folder 7:4
    - conference materials [5th Annual Cayce Health Professionals Symposium], 2000; Folder 7:5
    - conference materials [6th Annual Cayce Health Professionals Symposium], 2001; Folder 7:6
    - conference materials [Then and Now: The Medical Readings], 2001; Folder 7:7
    - consultation records, 1998-2003; Folder 7:8-7:9
  - Box 8
    - correspondence [Health and Rejuvenation Research Center], 1997-2001; Folder 8:1
    - financial records [Barden fund], 1998; Folder 8:2
    - financial records [Health and Rejuvenation Research Center], 1998-2002; Folder 8:3
    - financial records [Residential Programs], 1998-1999; Folder 8:4
    - health and wellness committee, 1992-1994; Folder 8:5
    - information packet [Health and Rejuvenation Research Center], 2001; Folder 8:6
    - job applications, 2000; Folder 8:7
    - lease agreement, 1999; Folder 8:8
    - letters to research participants, 1998; Folder 8:9
    - manual [global segmentelectrography], 1990; Folder 8:10
    - manual [Taylor-Johnson Temperament Analysis], 1996; Folder 8:11
  - Box 9
    - nameplate [Deborah Thompson, R.N.], undated; Folder 9:1
    - newsletter [Meridian Institute News], 1997-2000; Folder 9:2
    - newsletters [outside research organizations], 1998-2004; Folder 9:3
    - obesity questionnaire, 2004; Folder 9:4
    - osteoarthritis questionnaire, 2004; Folder 9:5
    - overviews [Cayce Health Database], 1998; Folder 9:6
    - personal file [Deborah Thompson, R.N.], 1997-1998; Folder 9:7
    - planning documents [Health Center], 1989-2000; Folder 9:8
  - Box 10
    - planning documents [Health and Rejuvenation Research Center], 1992-1998; Folder 10:1
    - proposals [A.R.E. Congress sharing group], 1993; Folder 10:2
    - proposal [Leydig Gland Project], undated; Folder 10:3
    - publications [A.R.E.], 1997-2004; Folder 10:4
    - real estate records, 1999; Folder 10:5
    - recipes, undated; Folder 10:6
    - recommendations for health readings research, 1992; Folder 10:7
    - report [Edgar Cayce Institute for Intuitive Studies], undated; Folder 10:8
    - reports [Meridian Institute], 2000-2002; Folder 10:9
  - Box 11
    - reports [outside research organizations], 1995-2000; Folder 11:1
    - report [Universal Concepts consulting], 1993; Folder 11:2
    - research materials [labyrinths], 1992-1999; Folder 11:3
    - research participant data [Cayce Comprehensive Symptom Inventory], 2000; Folder 11:4-11:5
    - research project: chronic fatigue, 2000; Folder 11:6
  - Box 12
    - Residential Research Program: Arthritis / Hypertension, 1998-1999; Folder 12:1
    - Residential Research Program: Psoriasis, 1999; Folder 12:2
    - Residential Research Program: Ulcerative Colitis, Irritable Bowel Syndrome, Crohn's Disease, 1999; Folder 12:3
    - scrapbook [Meridian Institute and Open House] Eric Mein, 1999; Folder 12:4
    - slideshow [ALS], undated; Folder 12:5
    - survey lecture materials [Deborah Thompson], 1999; Folder 12:6
    - trade catalogs, 1998-2004; Folder 12:7
    - workbook and manual [Cayce Comprehensive System Inventory], 2000; Folder 12:8
    - manuscript [Waking Nightmares: Case Studies in Anxiety] David McMillin, undated; Folder 12:9
    - book [The Treatment of Schizophrenia: A Holistic Approach] David McMillin, 1997; Item 12:10
    - book [Visualizing the Ra Ta Epic: Images of Ancient Egypt and Other Mysterious Places] David McMillin, 2004; Item 12:11
  - Box 13
    - book [A Holistic Approach: The Treatment of Depression] David McMillin, 1997; Item 13:1
    - book [Case Studies in Depression] David McMillin, 1997; Item 13:2
    - book [Case Studies in Schizophrenia] David McMillin, 1997; Item 13:3
    - book [Living Nightmares: Case Studies in Anxiety] David McMillin, 1992; Item 13:4
    - book [Principles and Techniques of Nerve Regeneration: Alzheimer's Disease and The Dementias], 1995; Item 13:5
    - CD [Anatomy, Physiology and Pathology in the Health Readings of Edgar Cayce, Disk 1] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:6
    - CD [Anatomy, Physiology and Pathology in the Health Readings of Edgar Cayce, Disk 2] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:7
    - CD [Anatomy, Physiology and Pathology in the Health Readings of Edgar Cayce, Disk 3] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:8
    - CD [books: Case Studies in Depression; A Holistic Approach to the Treatment of Depression] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:9
    - CD [books: Case Studies in Schizophrenia; The Treatment of Schizophrenia: A Holistic Approach] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:10
    - CD [books: Alzheimer's Disease and the Dementias] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:11
    - CD [David McMillin collected works], undated; Item 13:12
    - CD [Early American Dietetics and Nutrition] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:13
    - CD [Early American Energy Medicine] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:14
    - CD [Early American Herbal Medicine] David McMillin, 2007; Item 13:15
    - CD [Early American Hydrotherapy] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:16
    - CD [Edgar Cayce's Cosmology] David McMillin, 2007; Item 13:17
    - CD [Edgar Cayce on the Life and Times of Jesus] David McMillin, 2008; Item 13:18
    - CD [Edgar Cayce's Reincarnational History of Ancient Greece] David McMillin, 2010; Item 13:19
    - CD [Edgar Cayce's Reincarnational History of Ancient Rome] David McMillin, 2010; Item 13:20
    - CD [Edgar Cayce's Reincarnational History of Britain] David McMillin, 2015; Item 13:21
    - CD [Edgar Cayce's Reincarnational History of France] David McMillin, 2015; Item 13:22
    - CD [Electric Vibrator Therapy: Home and Professional Applications] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:23
    - CD [House of Clay: The Body-Soul Connection] David McMillin, 2007; Item 13:24
    - CD [Living Nightmares: Case Studies in Anxiety] David McMillin, 2007; Item 13:25
    - CD [Mental Health Lecture Series Disk 1: Schizophrenia] David McMillin, 2004; Item 13:26
    - CD [Mental Health Lecture Series Disk 2: Depression] David McMillin, 2004; Item 13:27
    - CD [Mental Health Lecture Series Disk 3: Anxiety; Mystical Experiences] David McMillin, 2004; Item 13:28
    - CD [Research Report Using the Edgar Cayce Medical Model] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:29
    - CD [Rivers of Light: A Personal Interpretation of the Revelation Based on the Readings of Edgar Cayce] David McMillin, 2007; Item 13:30
    - CD [Searching For God 1] David McMillin, 2011; Item 13:31
    - CD [Searching for God 2] David McMillin, 2011; Item 13:32
    - CD [Searching for God 3] David McMillin, 2011; Item 13:33
    - CD [Selections from the Abdominal and Pelvic Brain] Byron D. Robinson; David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:34
    - CD [The Radial Appliance and Wet Cell Battery] David McMillin; Douglas G. Richards, 2005; Item 13:35
    - CD [Visualizing the Ra Ta Epic] David McMillin, 2005; Item 13:36